<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
    <info>
        <name>Myconid</name>
        <author>Darklight3it
        </author>
        <update version="0.1.7">
            <file name="race-myconid.xml"
                  url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/aurorabuilder/elements/master/darklight3it/race-myconid.xml"/>
        </update>
    </info>

    <element name="Myconid" type="Race" source="Darklight3it's Custom" id="ID_DARKLIGHT3IT_RACE_MYCONID">
        <description>
            <p>Also called "mushroom men" or "fungus ones", myconids are intelligent, ambulatory fungi that live in the
                Underdark and the deepest, darkest depths of forests, seeking enlightenment and deploring violence. If
                approached peacefully, myconids gladly provide shelter or allow safe passage through their colonies.
                Violence taints their melds, so the myconids enter battle only in defense or as a last resort, viewing
                violence as part of the abhorrent nature of fleshy outsiders.
            </p>

            <p>Instead, the moving plants prefer a peaceable lifestyle, finding joy in pastoral commonality and shared
                happiness. Living in circles of roughly twenty myconids or settlements of larger groups, myconids
                cultivate
                nonsentient mushrooms and myconid sprouts in gardens. The precise 8-hour divisions of leisure, work, and
                melding creates a satisfying, if regimented, existence for these creatures, which regard such a
                lifestyle as
                completely ideal.
            </p>

            <h4>CIRCLES AND MELDS</h4>
            <p>The largest myconid in a colony is its sovereign, which presides over one or more social groups called
                circles, which live in quiet groves bereft of speech but exploding with the color of the diverse plants,
                fungi, and compost within. A circle of myconids that work, live, and meld together with the sovereign,
                which
                settles disputes and makes decisions to benefit the entire group.
            </p>

            <p>A meld is a form of communal meditation that allows myconids to transcend their damp, pastoral existence.
                The myconids' rapport spores bind the participants into a group consciousness. Hallucination spores then
                induce a shared dream that provides comfort and social interaction. Myconids consider melding to be an
                enlightening act and the purpose of their existence. They use it in the pursuit of higher consciousness,
                collective union, and spiritual apotheosis. Myconids also use their rapport spores to communicate
                telepathically with "softies" who come seeking shelter or conflict.
            </p>

            <h4>THE POWER OF SPORES</h4>
            <p>In addition to the versatile rapport spores and sublime hallucination spores, myconids use spores to
                reproduce. The new young are cultivated in gardens to become myconid sprouts, precocious young raised
                communally by the circle. Pacifying spores stun hostile intruders so the group might flee or wield a
                spore servant against them. Spore servants represent a terrifying aspect of the fungal race, the corpse
                of a
                once-living creature raised to serve as soldiers, guards, and scouts. Creatures controlled by these
                Animating Spores serve the myconids for weeks on end, until finally collapsing or another enemy destroys
                them.
            </p>

            <h4>ANATOMY OF A FUNGUS</h4>
            <p>Myconids are bipedal, with strong, squat bodies supported by strong, trunklike legs with vestigial toes.
                Each myconid has two arms that ends with a pair of fingers and a single thumb, more than sufficient for
                their simple agriculture. While their mycelial bodies provide notable durability, myconids are not
                typically
                skilled fighters. Myconids grow drastically over their lives, with sprouts barely reaching two feet and
                sovereigns towering to almost twelve.
            </p>

            <h4>FLIGHT FROM THE SUN</h4>
            <p>Myconids cannot survive in the sun. Direct light sickens them severely, and an hour of exposure kills
                them outright. Even the most durable of the adventuring myconids are not immune to the power of the sun.
                Wandering on the surface is a constant risk for most myconids, who instead flock to the Underdark or
                shelters of moist darkness in the oldest of forests where canopies of trees create a perpetual twilight.
                There they find shelter in damp marshes and springs, surrounded by moss and lesser mushrooms which they
                cultivate for food and grow for use as building materials.
            </p>
            <h4>MYCONID NAMES</h4>
            <p>Myconid names often sound nonsensical to outside ears, but are in fact derived from "softy" vocabulary.
                Myconids rarely use names within their circles, preferring rapport spores and the connections of melding
                to refer to each other in concept rather than word. They often take names from sounds that each myconid
                finds pleasing to the ear, borrowing from the world around them or from a wandering traveler offered
                hospitality in their grvoes. Others adopt mushroom-related vocabulary that they fine pleasant.
            </p>
            <p>
                <span class="feature">Myconid Names:</span>Basidia, Breberil, Brelup, Gasbide, Hebopbe, Loobamub, Phylo,
                Posbara, Rasharoo, Rumpadump, Stool, Yestabrod.
            </p>

            <h4>MYCONID TRAITS</h4>
            <p>Your myconid character has certain characteristics in common with all other myconids.</p>
            <p>
                <span class="feature">Ability Score Increase.</span>Your Wisdom score increases by 2.
                <br/>
                <span class="feature">Age.</span>Myconid have a brief period of adolescence whilst anchored to the
                ground sprouting. Reaching mental and physical maturity in a matter of hours, sometimes days. Myconid
                can live independently as long as basic nutritional needs are met, but will return to their homeland
                after a grand adventure and choose to die, returning peacefully to the loamy soil under the shade of
                their favorite tree, nestled into a crook of nostalgic trunk hollow.
                <br/>
                <span class="feature">Alignment.</span>Myconid instinctually tend to cultivate relationships with the
                animals and land around them in an act of mutualistic symbiosis. Thus, are observed embodying the
                tenants of the Neutral Good alignment in times of peace and prosperity. However,
                when their clan's survival is at risk a Myconid will not hesitate to act swiftly with a harsh True
                Neutral apathy only found in nature.
                <br/>
                <span class="feature">Size.</span>The physical size of a Myconid is directly proportional to how many
                hours it was able to safety sprout from the ground and how much room it had to grow. Small Myconid are
                around 3 feet tall. Medium Myconid range from 5 to 8 feet tall.
                <br/>
                <span class="feature">Speed.</span>Your base walking speed is 25 feet for small sized Myconid, 30 feet
                for medium size.
                <br/>
                <span class="feature">Superior Darkvision.</span>Accustomed to life underground, you have superior
                vision in dark
                and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 120 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in
                darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.
                <br/>
                <span class="feature">Sunlight Sensitivity.</span>You have disadvantage on attack rolls and on Wisdom
                (Perception) checks that rely on sight when you, the target of your attack, or whatever you are trying
                to perceive is in direct sunlight.
                <br/>
                <span class="feature">Size Matters.</span>Small size Myconid can move through the space of any creature
                that is of a size larger than them. That creature's space is still difficult terrain.
                <br/>
                <span class="feature">Certified Organic.</span>You have proficiency in the Nature skill.
                <br/>
                <span class="feature">Languages.</span>You can understand, read and write Common and Undercommon but not
                speak it.
                <br/>
                <span class="feature">Rapport Spores.</span>
                You may as an action, extend rapport spores in a 20-foot radius. These spores can go around corners and
                affect only creatures with an Intelligence of 2 or higher that aren't undead, constructs, or elementals.
                Affected creatures can communicate telepathically with one another while they are within 30 feet of each
                other. The effect lasts for 1 hour.
                <br/>
                <span class="feature">Subrace.</span>Two subraces of myconid are found among the worlds of D&amp;D.
                Choose one of these subraces.
                <br/>
            </p>
        </description>
        <sheet display="false"/>
        <setters>
            <set name="names" type="name">Basidia, Breberil, Brelup, Gasbide, Hebopbe, Loobamub, Phylo, Posbara,
                Rasharoo, Rumpadump, Stool, Yestabrod
            </set>
            <set name="names-format">{{name}}</set>
        </setters>
        <rules>
            <stat name="wisdom" value="2"/>
            <stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base"/>
            <grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_SMALL"/>
            <grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_SUPERIORDARKVISION"/>
            <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_SUNLIGHT_SENSITIVITY"/>
            <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_CERTIFIED_ORGANIC"/>
            <grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON"/>
            <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_DARKLIGHT3IT_RACIAL_TRAIT_MYCONID_SUBRACE"/>
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Certified Organic" type="Racial Trait" source="Custom" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_CERTIFIED_ORGANIC">
        <description>
            <p>You have proficiency in the Nature skill.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>You have proficiency in the Nature skill.
            </description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_SKILL_NATURE"/>
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Myconid Subrace" type="Racial Trait" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_DARKLIGHT3IT_RACIAL_TRAIT_MYCONID_SUBRACE">
        <description>
            <p>Two subraces of Myconid are found among the worlds of D&amp;D. Choose one
                of these subraces.
            </p>
        </description>
        <sheet display="false"/>
        <rules>
            <select type="Sub Race" name="Myconid Subrace" supports="Myconid"/>
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Underdark Myconid" type="Sub Race" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_DARKLIGHT3IT_SUB_RACE_UNDERDARK_MYCONID">
        <supports>Myconid</supports>
        <descriptionas>
            <p>Rarely, a chosen Myconid will brave the surface and go on pilgrimage. Being a strange creature in a
                strange land does not impede the bullish resolve these chosen few possess.
            </p>
            <p>
                <span class="feature">Ability Score Increase.</span>Your Constitution score increases by 1.
                <br/>
                <span class="feature">Meld Into Stone.</span>Once you reach 3rd level you can cast the Meld into Stone
                spell once with this feature. You regain the ability to cast it this way when you finish a long rest.
                Wisdom is your spellcasting ability .
                <br/>
                <span class="feature">Additional Language.</span>Myconid from the underdark have learned, albeit
                begrudgingly, the language of the creatures that frequently pillage and raid their communities in an
                effort to bargain with or threaten them. You know Undercommon.
                <br/>
            </p>
        </descriptionas>
        <sheet display="false"/>
        <rules>
            <stat name="constitution" value="1"/>
            <grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_UNDERCOMMON"/>
            <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_DARKLIGHT3IT_RACIAL_TRAIT_STONE_MELD"/>
        </rules>
    </element>

    <element name="Stone Meld" type="Racial Trait" source="Darklight3it's Custom" id="ID_DARKLIGHT3IT_RACIAL_TRAIT_STONE_MELD">
        <description>
            <p>Once you reach 3rd level you can cast the Meld into Stone spell once with this feature. You regain the
                ability to cast it this way when you finish a long rest. Wisdom is your spellcasting ability.
            </p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>You can cast the Meld into Stone spell once with this feature. You regain the ability to cast
                it this way when you finish a long rest. Wisdom is your spellcasting ability.
            </description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_MELD_INTO_STONE" level="3"/>
        </rules>
    </element>
</elements>